Finding Aid for Museum of Zoology (University of Michigan) records 1876-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Museum of Zoology (University of Michigan) records 1876-1999 1910-1955 1975-1989
University of Michigan. Museum of Zoology.
A research and teaching museum at the University of Michigan, one of four units of the University Museum. Records include museum directors' topical files and correspondence; minutes, reports, and correspondence of museum committees; photographs; and various publications, largely about the museum. Subjects concern the collections, expeditions, and other activities of the museum, especially during the administrations of directors Joseph B. Steere, Alexander Ruthven, Frederick Gaige, James S. Rogers, and Theodore Hubbell.
91429 Bimu C450 2
7.5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were transferred from the Museum of Zoology (Donor No. 837 ) in 1990. Outsize records transferred in 1993. Additional records were received in 1993.
The records are open for research.
The Museum of Zoology of the University of Michigan is a research and teaching unit organized for the study of the evolution, distribution, and systematic relationships of animals. It is one of four separate museums which together make up the University Museums (the official title for this assembly of natural history museums since 1928). The three other museums are the Museum of Paleontology, the Museum of Anthropology, and the Exhibit Museum. Along with the University Herbarium and a service unit these museums are all located in the Ruthven Museums Building on central campus.
Although an administratively separate institution since 1913, the Museum of Zoology is closely intertwined with the University Museums as a whole. Both trace their roots back to the establishment of the university as a state institution in 1837 when the Michigan Legislature authorized the purchase of a "cabinet of natural history." Through the mid-nineteenth century, donations of zoological specimens were received by the university from interested individuals and through a special arrangement with the Smithsonian Institution. At that time, it was difficult to find storage space for this material and specimens were frequently housed in attics and other less than ideal locations. In 1878, the president's report noted the danger of exposing "our rare and extensive scientific collections to the risk of destruction by fire for the lack of new fire-proof buildings."
Under the direction of Joseph Beal Steere (curator of the Museum of Natural History from 1876 to 1894), the museum moved to the first University Museum Building on State Street in 1881. Steere had obtained a large and impressive collection of zoological specimens from South America and the Far East during his trip around the world from 1870 to 1875 and this large accession provided the momentum for the erection of the new building designed by William Le Baron Jenney. At the same time, the Board of Regents adopted a new set of rules concerning university collections. In summary, the regents said that professors in charge of instruction in the various fields of natural history "shall be the curators of the corresponding collections in the Museum of Natural History." Problems with this arrangement proved to be twofold. First, while some professors (especially the zoologists) took an active interest in collection, others did not, resulting in the uneven development of collections. Second, while the president of the university was given general oversight of the relations of the museums to each other, no provision was made for a director of the Museum of Natural History.
These problems were finally addressed in 1913. As a result of the collecting priorities of Steere and his successors the museum had developed a strong zoological orientation while other collections languished. Acknowledging that fact, the regents, in 1913, changed the name of the Museum of Natural History to the Museum of Zoology and formally recognized the Museum of Zoology as a separate administrative unit. At the same time, Alexander Grant Ruthven, who had been curator of the museum since receiving his Ph.D. in zoology in 1906, became director of the museum. For Ruthven, the museum was an essential tool for deciphering the course and mechanisms of evolution and from his tenure forward, the primacy of zoological collection and research over the museum's exhibit functions was assured.
Between 1913 and 1927, the museum staff grew from 5 to 14, its collections more than quadrupled and six major divisions were created each with a full-time curator. In addition to the permanent staff, Ruthven was able to attract a group of influential amateur naturalists whose informal organization was known as the Detroit Naturalists Club or simply the Detroit Club. These amateurs not only contributed financially to the museum but several, such as Bryant Walker, William Newcomb, and E.B. Williamson, became nationally recognized authorities in various sub-fields of zoology as well as honorary curators of the museum. The tradition of collecting expeditions begun by Steere also continued during Ruthven's tenure with numerous new expeditions, especially to South America.
By the mid-1920s, the need for a new building was clearly recognized. In 1925, the Michigan legislature appropriated the funds and in 1928 the new University Museums Building (today, known as the Ruthven Museums Building) was opened. The new museum housed the Museum of Zoology, as well as the newly independent Museums of Anthropology and Paleontology, and the University Herbarium. Ruthven, who had actively collaborated with architect Albert Kahn in the design of the new building, became director of the University Museums as well as director of the Museum of Zoology.
In 1929, Ruthven resigned as director of the Museum of Zoology to become president of the university and Frederick Gaige was appointed the new director. Gaige had been associated with the museum since 1908. He had been curator of insects, a close collaborator with Ruthven, and assistant director. Gaige's wife (Helen Thompson Gaige) continued as curator of amphibians and soon assumed increasing responsibility for the direction of graduate instruction. During Gaige's directorship, the university accepted the gift of the Edwin S. George Reserve, in Pinkney, for zoological study (1930) and the museum continued to increase its holdings. In 1936, Ruthven also stepped down as director of the University Museums and, in 1944, the duties of director passed to an operating committee made up of the directors of the four individual museums.
In 1945, Frederick Gaige retired as director of the Museum of Zoology. Despite indications of some internal controversy over Gaige's leadership in the late 1930s, the museum maintained its teaching and research commitments during the difficult years of the depression and the war. In 1947, James Speed Rogers was appointed director of the Museum of Zoology. Rogers, an authority on craneflies and a former student of both Ruthven and Gaige returned to the University of Michigan from the University of Florida where he had been professor of biology since 1922. Many new collections were added during Rogers' tenure and the graduate program expanded.
Rogers died unexpectedly in 1955 and was succeeded in 1956 by Theodore H. Hubbell. One of Hubbell's early tasks was the resolution of a long-standing problem. In 1928, the regents had adopted a policy which allowed each museum to work out its own co-operative arrangement with the teaching departments in its particular discipline. In practice, teaching arrangements varied widely among the various museums and for individuals within specific museums. In 1956, an administrative reorganization required future appointments to be half-time in the museum and half-time in a teaching department. This change gave full professorial rank and teaching responsibilities to new museum appointees and to current staff who chose to request it.
In 1968, with Hubbell's retirement, Nelson G. Hairston became director of the Museum of Zoology. By 1972, the museum housed some seven million specimens. Today, the museum is recognized internationally especially for its extensive collection of North American fresh water fish and for its collection of insects. Researchers continue to come from around the world to examine these and other collections in the Museum of Zoology.
The Museum of Zoology record group includes not so much the complete records of the Museum of Zoology but rather significant documents pertaining to its history which have been assembled and preserved over the years by the museum staff. The photographs in this collection are of special interest since they document the early years of the museum, especially under Alexander Grant Ruthven. The records have been divided into six series: Directors' Topical Files; Directors' Correspondence; Committee Minutes, Reports, and Correspondence; Index Card Files; Photographs; and Publications.
Subjects:
Gaige, Frederick M.; Hubbell, Theodore Huntington, 1897-1989.; Rogers, J. Speed (James Speed), 1892-1955; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-1971.; Steere, Joseph Beal, 1842-1940.; Zoology.
- Directors' Topical Files
  The Directors' Topical Files (1.5 linear feet) are alphabetically arranged and contain a wide range of subjects relating to the museum. Researchers interested in a general overview of the museum should consult material in the three folders "Histories of the Museum." In addition, brief biographical sketches and obituaries of some past directors and curators may be found in the folders "Biographical Information." The state of the museum at specific points in time can also be gleaned from the folders of occasional "Reports" of directors and curators from 1907 to 1974. These particular reports are not duplicates of reports found in the yearly bound volumes of The President's Report which should also be consulted for reports of the Museum of Zoology. Two important events in the museums history are documented in the following folders: "Name change of museum, 1913" and "Administrative reorganization, 1954-1956."
  Those interested in early twentieth-century expeditions organized by the museum should consult "Expeditions" and folders for specific expeditions within this folder group. In general, these folders contain information on the planning of expeditions, some correspondence during these trips, and newspaper accounts. However, few detailed reports on the results of any expeditions are included.
  Architectural historians and others interested in the construction of the 1928 museum buildings will find only a few blueprints and limited correspondence in the "Museum Building" folders. However, more detailed reports and correspondence exist in these folders regarding the 1963 addition to the museum building. For additional information on the design of the museum building, researchers should consult the Alexander Ruthven collection which is also in the Bentley Library.
  Over the years, various properties were acquired by the university for the purpose of teaching and research in the natural sciences. Those interested in the acquisition of and research conducted at these Michigan sites should consult the following folders: "George Reserve (Pinkney)"; "Missaukee Preserve (Lake City)"; and "Sharon Hollow Woods (Washtenaw County)." Information on other properties, such as Stinchfield Woods (Ann Arbor) and Mud Lake Bog (Washtenaw County) may be found in the folders "University Committee on Lands."
  Finally, a thirty-four page handwritten description of the National Museum Building in Washington, D.C. at the time of inauguration in 1881 (author unknown) is a document of special historical interest. This manuscript includes commentary on the proper arrangement of a natural history museum in the nineteenth century as well as description of the building. It may be found in the folder "National Museum Building."
  - Administrative reorganization 1954-1956 (Box 1)
  - Andrews collection of coleoptera 1951 (Box 1)
  - Biographical Information
    - Frederick M. Gaige (Box 1)
    - Helen Thompson Gaige (Box 1)
    - Norman E. Hartweg (Box 1)
    - Claude W. Hibbard (Box 1)
    - Clarence Hamilton Kennedy (Box 1)
    - Ada Olson (Box 1)
    - J. Speed Rogers (Box 1)
    - Alexander Grant Ruthven (Box 1)
    - Josselyn Van Tyne (Box 1)
    - Edward Bruce Williamson (Box 1)
  - Budgets and appointments 1895-1972, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Budgets and Salaries 1925/25-1949/50 (Box 1)
  - Center for Tropical Studies 1956-1963 (Box 1)
  - Cleveland Museum of Natural History 1959-1976 (Box 1)
  - College of Literature, Science and the Arts 1949-1950 (Box 1)
    (Museum of Zoology membership proposed)
  - Committee on Nomenclature 1924-1925 (Box 1)
  - Department of Zoology (selection of chairman) 1965 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Naturalists Club 1906-1938 (Box 1)
  - Divisions of the museum
    - Birds 1926-1927 (Box 1)
    - Crustaceans 1903-1953 (Box 1)
    - Fishes 1926-1927 (Box 1)
    - Insects 1923-1965 (Box 1)
    - Mammals 1933-1956 (Box 1)
    - Reptiles and amphibians 1945-1980 (Box 1)
  - Exhibits and public relations 1929-1972 (Box 1)
  - Expeditions
    - British Guiana 1914 (Box 1)
    - British Guiana 1925 (Box 1)
    - Columbia 1913 (Box 1)
    - Charity Island, Michigan 1910 (Box 1)
    - German West Africa 1910 (Box 1)
    - Mexico 1910 (Box 1)
    - Porcupine Mountains, Michigan 1904-1912 (Box 1)
    - South Africa 1924 (Box 1)
    - Texas 1914, 1916 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous expeditions and local field trips 1907-1947 (Box 1)
  - Frederick M. Gaige Research Fund 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - Geological Survey 1910 (Box 1)
  - George Reserve (Pinkney, Michigan)
    - Deer research 1965-1967 (Box 1)
    - General 1926-1972 (Box 1)
    - Meteorological research facility 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Herbarium 1927-1960 (Box 1)
  - Histories of the Museum of Zoology, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Honorary curators 1910-1972 (Box 1)
  - Insectary 1965 (Box 1)
  - Institute of Malacology 1962-1966 (Box 1)
  - Marsh Collection of Mollusks 1958-1961 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous files of the director
    - T. H. Hubbell 1959-1967 (Box 1)
    - Nelson Hairston 1961-1969 (Box 1)
    - Alexander Ruthven 1909-1930 (Box 1)
  - Missaukee Preserve 1922-1928 (Lake City, Michigan) (Box 1)
  - Monetary values of collections 1953-1962 (Box 1)
  - Museum building (built in 1880)
    - Description of building by Regent Cook circa 1895 (Box 1)
    - Description of building prior to demolition 1958 (Box 1)
  - Museum building (built in 1928)
    - Addition 1964
      - Blueprints 1963 (Box 1)
      - National Science Foundation grant 1961 (Box 1)
      - Open house and news releases May 1964 (Box 1)
      - Preliminary planning 1959-1963 (Box 1)
    - Blueprints 1926-1928 (Box 1)
    - Remodeling 1953-1960 (Box 1)
    - Safety 1942-1960 (Box 1)
  - Name change of museum 1913 (Box 2)
  - National Museum building, Washington, D.C. 1881 (Box 2)
    (description at time of inauguration possibly by J.B. Steere)
  - Organizational chart 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - Procedures and policies 1920s (Box 2)
  - Procedures and policies 1957-1975 (Box 2)
  - Program in Environmental Biology (proposed) 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Publications 1922-1980, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Regents of the University of Michigan 1912-1919 (Box 2)
  - Reports
    - "Report of the Director of the Museum" 1917 (Box 2)
    - "Relation of the University Museums to Teaching Departments of the University" April 6, 1927 (Box 2)
    - "Report on Museum of Zoology Research" February 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Museum of Zoology: Survey of Needs" December 13, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Report on the Museum of Zoology" November 14, 1956 (Box 2)
    - "A Report on the Museum of Zoology" April 19, 1961 (Box 2)
    - "Report to the Museum of Zoology" March 18, 1963 (Box 2)
    - "Annual Report of the Museum of Zoology" 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous reports 1905-1967 (Box 2)
  - Royal Ontario Museum 1952-1968 (molluscs) (Box 2)
  - Scholarships and assistantships 1923-1926 (Box 2)
  - Sharon Hollow Woods 1964-1966 (Box 2)
  - Specimen exchanges 1915-1928 (Box 2)
  - Specimen preparation 1956-1970 (Box 2)
  - Staff teas 1927-1928 (Box 2)
  - Trust funds 1954-1960 (Box 2)
  - University Committee on Lands 1949-1971, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Directors' Correspondence
  The Directors' Correspondence (0.5 linear feet) is alphabetically arranged and includes both incoming and outgoing correspondence. This series consists primarily of the correspondence of J. Speed Rogers who was director of the museum from 1947 to 1955. His correspondence, however, extends back to the early 1920s when he was a graduate student at the University of Michigan and to the period when he was a professor at the University of Florida (1922-1947). Rogers maintained a close association with the University of Michigan throughout this period. Hence, much of this early correspondence also relates to the Museum of Zoology. Several folders may be of special interest. Researchers interested in the controversy over Gaige's directorship in the late 1930s should consult Roger's correspondence with Josselyn Van Tyne. Also, some discussion of the impact of the Scopes trial on the teaching of zoology may be found in Roger's correspondence with Frank Thone (several letters). Some correspondence of other directors is also included in this series. The folder "J.B. Steere" includes a few letters addressed to Steere. Correspondence of Alexander Ruthven and Frederick Gaige is also represented to a limited extent.
  - Bass, John F. Jr. 1934-1936 (Bass Biological Laboratory) (Box 2)
  - Bates, Marston 1928-1952, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Berner, Lewis 1941-1945 (Box 2)
  - Blair, Frank W. 1935-1946 (Box 2)
  - Boardman, E.T. 1929-1946 (Box 2)
  - Burt, William H. 1946 (Box 2)
  - Byers, C. Francis 1928-1931 (Box 2)
  - Cantrall, Irving 1935-1971 (Box 2)
  - Carr, A.F. 1934-1946 (Box 2)
  - Cummins, Harold 1918-1925 (Box 2)
  - Fargo, William G. 1936-1954 (Box 2)
    (Jackson County property)
  - Gaige, Frederick 1917-1943, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - George, Col. Edwin S. 1947-1951 (Box 2)
    (George Reserve)
  - Giovannoli, Leonard 1930-1946 (Box 2)
  - Goodrich, Calvin 1948 (Box 2)
  - Harkness, W.J.K. 1939-1943 (Box 2)
  - Hubbs, Carl 1927-1943 (Box 2)
  - Hutchins, H.B. 1911-1920 (Box 2)
  - McGraw-Hill Book Company 1938-1943 (Box 2)
  - Mayr, Ernest 1961-1967 (Box 2)
  - Needham, James G. 1933-1944 (Box 2)
  - Norris, Harry Waldo 1920-1939 (Box 2)
  - Perkins, John 1949 (Box 2)
  - Pierce, E. Lowe 1936-1945 (Box 2)
  - Steere, J.B. 1876-1891 (Box 2)
  - Thompson, Crystal 1919-1928 (Box 2)
  - Thone, Frank 1923-1928 (Box 2)
  - Townsend, Homer 1936-1937 (Box 2)
  - Van Der Schalie, Henry 1964-1981 (Box 2)
  - Van Tyne, Josselyn 1938-1940 (Box 2)
  - Walker, Fred 1925-1935 (Box 2)
  - Wallace, H.K. 1930-1945 (Box 2)
  - Welch, Paul S. 1929-1938 (Box 2)
- Committee Minutes, Reports, and Correspondence
  The series Committee Minutes, Reports, and Correspondence (0.5 linear feet) is subdivided into four museum committees. Two of these were University Museums committees (the operating committee and the Museum advisory board) and two were Museum of Zoology committees (the executive committee and the curators committee).
  The purpose of the operating committee of the University Museums was to bring together the directors of the individual museums for discussions and joint decision-making. In 1944, the functions of the director of the University Museums were transferred to this committee. Minutes, reports and correspondence of the operating committee are included for the years 1939 to 1957. The museum advisory board included members of the operating committee as well as the deans of several other university units. The board acted in "an advisory capacity to the directors of the associated museum units and to the President and Board of Regents in connection with matters of policy involving the University Museums as a whole and their relationship to the educational programs of the University." Minutes, reports, and correspondence exist for the advisory board for 1945-1946 and again for 1953-1955 when the board was reconstituted.
  The executive committee of the Museum of Zoology was composed of the senior members of the museum staff. The minutes of this committee document the museum's history from 1938 to 1948. Finally, the curators committee included the curators of the various divisions of the Museum of Zoology and minutes of their meetings may be found for the years 1947 to 1949.
  - University Museums
    - Operating Committee
      - Correspondence 1939-1957 (Box 3)
      - Minutes 1945-1956, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Reports 1944-1945 (Box 3)
    - Museum Advisory Board minutes 1945-1955 (Box 3)
      (includes some correspondence)
  - Museum of Zoology
    - Executive Committee minutes
      - 1938-1948, 8 folders (Box 3)
      - 1959-1961 (Box 3)
        (scattered)
    - Curators Committee minutes 1947-1949 (Box 3)
- Index Card Files, 3 boxes; 5 linear feet
  The series Index Card Files (0.5 linear feet) includes three boxes of typewritten index cards recording the proceedings of the Board of Regents on matters relating to the Museum of Zoology. Compiled, probably in the 1920s and 1930s, these card files chronicle events from the authorization to set up a "cabinet of natural history" in 1837 until 1939. The card files are alphabetically arranged by subject and then chronologically arranged within subjects. Taken together, the approximately 2,000 cards in this index provide an important chronology for a history of the museum.
  - Index to Regents Proceedings, 1837-1939, concerning the Museum of Zoology (Box 3)
- Photographs
  The Photographs (0.5 linear feet) are a major strength of this collection. Many date from the early part of the twentieth century and they are especially well-identified. The series has been subdivided into three parts: photographs of individuals, of groups, and of museum buildings. Certain photograph folders may be of special interest. Several excellent photographs of Alexander Grant Ruthven as a young man may be found among the photographs of individuals. The folder "Detroit Naturalist Club" contains photographs of this group both in formal settings and on field trips. Most of these photographs date from before 1920. There are several photographs of the first museum building which was built in 1880 and demolished in 1958. Also, this series includes a photograph album containing some 70 photographs by M.L. Winslow showing the construction of the University Museums building from March 2 to October 10, 1927, and an album of photographs taken on various Museum-sponsored expeditions.
  - Individuals
    - Andrews, A.W. (Box 4)
    - Blanchard, Frank (Box 4)
    - Blossom, Philip Moss (Box 4)
    - Billington, Cecil (Box 4)
    - Case, Ermine Cowles (Box 4)
    - Cratty, R.J. (Box 4)
    - Creaser, Eddie (Box 4)
    - Dice, Lee R. (Box 4)
    - Gaige, Frederick M. (Box 4)
    - Gaige, Helen Thompson (Box 4)
    - George, Col. Edwin S. (Box 4)
    - Goodrich, Calvin (Box 4)
    - Hinsdale, W.B. (photograph of bust by W. Angell) (Box 4)
    - Hubbell, Theodore H. (Box 4)
    - Hubbs, Carl L. and Laura Hubbs (Box 4)
    - Pearse, A.S (Box 4)
    - Rogers, James Speed (Box 4)
    - Ruthven, Alexander Grant (Box 4)
    - Steere, J.B (Box 4)
    - Trinkle, Donald (Box 4)
    - Walker, Bryant (Box 4)
    - Walker, Charles Francis (Box 4)
    - Wing, Leonard W. (Box 4)
    - Williamson, E.B (Box 4)
    - Wood, Norman A. (Box 4)
    - Unidentified individuals (Box 4)
  - Groups
    - American Society of Ichthyologists and Herpetologists 1947 (Box 4)
    - Detroit Naturalists Club 1908-1939 (Box 4)
    - Entomology students 1918 (Box 4)
    - George Reserve 1965 (Box 4)